Guide to the Overbrook Press Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Overbrook Press records
1918-1979
1934-1969
GEN MSS 961
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
51.75
106 boxes + 6 broadside folders
The Overbrook Press Records contain correspondence, office files, and production files documenting the operations and publications of the Overbrook Press. The records also hold small group of Frank Altschul's personal papers, a collection of printed material, mostly ephemera, published by peer presses, professional and private associations and clubs, and a group of type specimens from American and European typefounders. The Production Files form the most significant part of the records, and contain original and carbon typescripts, manuscripts, printed sources or copies of source text, designs and layout pages, dummies, proofs, and galleys; some files hold correspondence, published reviews, and final copies of the publications as well as original artwork, silkscreen stencils, bookbinding stamps, and a collection of paper samples. Correspondents include various authors and illustrators including T. M. Cleland, W. A. Dwiggins, William Einstein, Jean Hugo, Bruce Rogers, and Rudolph Ruzicka. Also present are the photoengravings used for printing illustrations and decorations in press publications. The latest item in the collection is an Overbrook Press tribute broadside which was printed by Altschul's nephew Charles Altschul at Yale University in 1979.
Overbrook Press
Einstein, William, 1907-1972
Lobel-Riche, Alméry, 1880-1950
Nason, Thomas W. (Thomas Willoughby), 1889-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frank Altschul (Yale 1908) to the Yale University Library Arts of the Book Collection, 1977-1982. Transferred from Arts of the Book Collection to Beinecke Library, 2003-2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Columbia University Library holds the remainder of the Overbrook Press Records (MS 0959) as well as the Frank Altschul Papers (MS 0022).
Overbrook Press (1934-1969)
Overbrook Press was established in 1934 by financier and philanthropist Frank Altschul in a remodeled pigpen on his estate Overbrook Farm, at 356 Riverbank Road in Stamford, Connecticut. Interested in the craft of printing since childhood, Altschul hired Margaret B. Evans as resident designer and compositor; she remained with the press until 1944 and was succeeded by John Lyons. John McNamara served as pressman from 1934 to 1954, followed by Frederick Warns. Between 1934 and 1969, when it issued its last publications, Overbrook Press produced more than 150 limited edition books, pamphlets, and broadsides, plus a wide variety of ephemera, for people, organizations, and events of interest to Altschul, his family, and friends. The press's books regularly won awards for their design and production quality; the texts favored politics, foreign relations, chess, printing, graphic arts, and literature as illustrated by artists including T. M. Cleland, W. A. Dwiggins, William Einstein, Jean Hugo, and Rudolph Ruzicka.
A chronology of the key activities and publications of the Overbrook Press was compiled at the Arts of the Book Collection in 1988; a copy is located in Box 1.
Frank Altschul (1887-1981)
Frank Altschul was born in San Francisco on April 21, 1887, to Charles and Camilla Mandlebaum Altschul; Charles Altschul, an investment banker with the firm Lazard Frères & Company, relocated the family to New York in 1901. Frank Altschul attended Yale University, graduating in 1908, after which he traveled in Europe for two years before returning to New York to start a career in finance with Lazard Frères. He served in the Army in France during World War I, and was awarded the Legion of Honor by the French government. Altschul became a senior partner at Lazard Frères in 1943, and five years later chairman of the board of the General American Investors Corporation. He served on the governing committee of the New York Stock Exchange, was a director of the English-Speaking Union, an officer of the Woodrow Wilson Foundation and the National Planning Association, and was involved with the Council of Foreign Relations for almost forty years. He received honorary degrees from Yale University in 1967 and Columbia University in 1971.
In 1913 Altschul married Helen Lehman Goodhart (1887-1985), a 1907 graduate of Barnard College and a niece of the prominent New York politician Herbert H. Lehman. The Altschuls raised their children Charles, Margaret, Edith, and Arthur at their homes in New York City and at Overbrook Farm, an estate along the Mianus River in Stamford, Connecticut. Edith Altschul (1917-2003) married Robert Claverhouse Graham (1913-1994, Yale 1936), a partner in the James Graham Gallery in New York.
In addition to producing his own, Altschul collected exemplars of fine printing from America and Europe, in particular France. He also formed a library of works related to the typographic arts, including eighteenth- and nineteenth-century printers manuals, type specimens, and bibliographies. His book collections were transferred to Yale University following his death in Stamford on May 29, 1981, where they were divided between the Beinecke Library and the Arts of the Book Collection at Sterling Memorial Library. The equipment from the Overbrook Press was given to Yale University in 1977 by Altschul, and distributed to the Bibliographical Press at Sterling Memorial Library, press rooms in the university's colleges, and other departments on campus.
Scope and Contents
The Overbrook Press Records contain correspondence, office files, and production files documenting the operations and publications of the press. The records also include a small group of Frank Altschul's personal papers, a collection of printed material, mostly ephemera, published by peer presses, professional and private associations and clubs, and a group of type specimens from American and European typefounders. The Production Files form the most significant part of the records, and contain original and carbon typescripts, manuscripts, printed sources or copies of source text, designs and layout pages, dummies, proofs, and galleys; some files hold correspondence, published reviews, and final copies of the publications as well as original artwork, silkscreen stencils, bookbinding stamps, and a collection of paper samples. Also present are the photoengravings used for printing illustrations and decorations in press publications. The latest item in the collection is an Overbrook Press tribute broadside which was printed by Altschul's nephew Charles Altschul at Yale University in 1979.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence and Office Files, 1926-1979. II. Frank Altschul Personal Papers, 1918-1979. III. Production Files, 1934-1969. IV. Printed Material. V. Photoengravings and Printing Blocks.
Language(s)
In English and French.
Book design -- Connecticut -- Stamford; Graphic arts -- United States; Illustration of books -- 20th Century; Letterpress printing -- Connecticut -- Stamford; Printers -- Connecticut -- Stamford; Printing -- Specimens; Private presses -- Connecticut -- Stamford; Publishers and publishing -- Connecticut -- Stamford; Ephemera (general object genre) -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrations (layout features) -- United States -- 20th Century; Lithographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Printing plates -- France -- 20th Century; Printing plates -- United States -- 20th Century; Progressive proofs -- United States -- 20th Century; Proofs (prints by function) -- United States -- 20th Century; Screens (screen printing equipment) -- United States -- 20th Century; Stamps (tools) -- United States -- 20th Century; Printers -- Connecticut -- Stamford -- 20th Century; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Cleland, T. M. (Thomas Maitland), 1880-1964; Dwiggins, W. A. (William Addison), 1880-1956; Einstein, William, 1907-1972; Evans, Margaret B.; Hugo, Jean, 1894-1984; Lobel-Riche, Alméry, 1880-1950; Nason, Thomas W. (Thomas Willoughby), 1889-1971; Ruzicka, Rudolph, 1883-1978; Overbrook Press
- Correspondence and Office Files, 1926-1979; Series I; 2.3; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Office Files.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains business correspondence as well as a group of files related to press business but generally not to specific publications. In addition to letters, the Correspondence subseries holds many receipts and invoices for the purchase of type, equipment, paper, and other materials. Additional Margaret Evans correspondence appears in the chronologically arranged folders, as well as in Series III. Production Files.
  - Correspondence
    - Andrade, B. J. de C., 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Evans, Margaret B., 1933-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Reinhardt, Ad, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Rogers, Bruce, 1938-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ruzicka, Rudolph, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Christmas cards and pamphlets received by the press, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General correspondence, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9-15)
    - General correspondence, 1939-1953 (Box 3, Folder 16-29)
    - General correspondence, 1954-1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 30-39)
  - Office Files
    - American Type Founders Sales Corporation estimates for outfitting press room, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Book reviews, 1935-1950, undated (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
    - Calendier historial, photostatic copy, undated
    - Estimate - Bushell Press, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Evans, Margaret B., "Work In Progress" report, 1944 Jan 28 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Gideonse, Harry D., et al, "Memorandum on the Need for a New Journal on Higher Education in the United States," typescript carbon, corrected, 1943 Mar 9 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Gillis, Walter, Recollections of the Gillis Press and Its Work During Fifty Years, plates, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Hersey, John, Frank Altschul and the Overbrook Press, layouts and proofs, 1979
      Memorial broadside printed by Charles Altschul at Pierson College, Yale University, using equipment given to the college by Frank Altschul.
    - Historical data: typescripts and correspondence, 1938, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 47)
      General note
      Essays prepared for publication in The Colophon Annual of Bookmaking and American Notes & Queries.
    - Incorporation papers, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Mailing lists, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - "Memo to City Desks," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent: "Twenty sonnets," photostatic copy from Reedy's Mirror, undated
    - Notebook with overtime accounts, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Overbrook Press exhibition signs, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Press mark registration, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Publication lists, circa 1947-1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - "Pythia" typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Receipts, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "Samuel Langhorne Clemens," photostat of manuscript in the Pierpont Morgan Library, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Shotwell, James T., "The Colleague" typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - "Sir William and His Court," typescript with letter from John Ferguson, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - "Some Satisfied Customers," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - U. S. Senate, The Printing Industry and the Proposed Copyright Convention, Memoranda Regarding Probable Effects on the Printing Industry of Adoption of the Copyright Convention, 1939 July 20 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - War Production Board, Printing & Publishing Division, "Bulletin to Book Publishers", 1943 December (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified typescripts and manuscripts, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Index card file of customers and contacts, undated (Box 6)
- Frank Altschul Personal Papers, 1918-1979; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  The series contains material related to Altschul's personal life, including photographs of Overbrook Farm and a production file for a publication he managed for the Grolier Club prior to the founding of his Overbrook Press.
  - Printing plate with etched image by Alméry Lobel-Riche, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Cleland, T. M. "Life in Eighteenth-Century France"; four prints, undated
  - Grolier Club
    - Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Production file for Louis V. Ledoux, A Descriptive Catalogue of an Exhibition of Japanese Figure Prints, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 66)
      Altschul served as production manager for this Grolier Club publication.
  - Identification papers, United States War Department, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Illuminated manuscript leaf, undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Illuminated printed leaf from the fables of Aesop, undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Nason, Thomas W., wood engraving of gambrel-roofed house, undated
  - National Committee for a Free Europe, President's Report, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Overbrook Farm map: pen and ink drawing by Dana Perry, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Overbrook Farm photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 72-73)
  - Telephone book, undated (Box 7, Folder 74)
- Production Files, 1934-1969; Series III; 15; (36 boxes)
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Publications, Ephemera, and Other Production Material. Publications and Ephemera are arranged alphabetically by the author's name or the title of the work.
  The series holds files for Overbrook Press publications and ephemera, as well as additional materials related to design and publishing. The files may contain original and carbon typescripts, manuscripts, printed sources or copies of source text, designs and mechanicals, dummies, page proofs, and galleys, as well as project correspondence, advertising, reviews, and copies of the publications. Notable in the first subseries are the original graphite drawings by William Einstein for the book Affaire Crainquebille, by Anatole France, and a set of silkscreen stencils used to print the T. M. Cleland illustrations for Histoire du Chevalier des Grieux et de Manon Lescaut, by Abbé Prévost.
  The third subseries, Other Production Materials, holds bindings samples, trial press sheets, brass stamps for titling and decorating bindings, and various paper samples.
  Additional correspondence relating to specific press projects may also be found in Series I. Correspondence, boxes 1 through 4.
  - Publications
    - Adams, Frederick B., Jr., Radical Literature in America: An Address; to which is appended a catalogue of an exhibition held at the Grolier Club in New York City, 1938-1939 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - An Address to the People of the United States, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 76-77)
    - Addresses on the Occasion of the Presentation of the Woodrow Wilson Award for Distinguished Service to Dean Gooderham Acheson, October 1, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Adverse Report of the Committee on the Judiciary on a Bill to Reorganize the Judicial Branch of the Government, 1937
    - Aldington, Richard, A Dream in Luxembourg, 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 79-80)
    - Aldrich, Amey, Fifty Years Ago: Early Days of the Cosmopolitan Club: An Address, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Alfred Whitney Griswold, 1906-1963: In Memoriam, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 82-83)
    - Allen, Edgar W. and Eric M. Hassberg, eds., To Alain White, a tribute from his friends on the occasion of his sixty-fifth birthday, March the third, 1945, edited by Edgar W. Allen and Eric M. Hassberg (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Altschul, Charles, The Influence of England: from the American Revolution in our School Text-Books, 1954
    - Altschul, Julius, Vera Lillian Heller and John Walter Behrend: Address Delivered... at the Wedding Reception, 1947 Sep 6 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Am Grabe von Otto Jeidels: aus der Erinnerung Nachgeschrieben Graf G. Kanitz, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts, Catalogue of an Exhibition of the Work of Edwin and Robert Grabhorn of San Francisco... Held by the American Institute of Graphic Arts, New York, 1942, cover by Overbrook Press (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Analita, "Overbrook Farm: A Dangerous Place", undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, The Task - And Price - of World Leadership, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Ballantine, Arthur A.
      - A Few Poems, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 90)
      - Uncle Charlie & Sir William and His Court, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 91-92)
    - Ballantine, William Gay, William Gay Ballantine: Biographical Notes Together With Selected Addresses, Essays & Miscellaneous Poems, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Baruch, Bernard M. Freedom for Man - A World Safe for Mankind: An Address, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 94-95)
    - Bennett, Arnold, A Love Affair, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Benton, William, Brien McMahon: A Tribute, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Bierce, Ambrose, "A Horseman in the Sky", undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Bingham, June, Do Cows Have Neuroses?, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Brewster, Kingman, Style, Pluck & Integrity: The Griswold legacy, an evaluation, [by] Kingman Brewster ... and the Baccalaureate address, Yale University, June, 1958 [by] A. Whitney Griswold (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - Brewster, Kingman, Style, Pluck & Integrity: The Griswold legacy, an evaluation, [by] Kingman Brewster ... and the Baccalaureate address, Yale University, June, 1958 [by] A. Whitney Griswold (Box 10, Folder 101-103)
    - A Brief Narrative of the Case and Tryal of John Peter Zenger, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Bridges, Styles, Statement by Senator Styles Bridges on the Floor of the Senate of the United States, March 24, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Burke, Edmund, "Because Half a Dozen Grasshoppers...", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Buschke, Albrecht, et al., The Two-Move Chess Problem in the Soviet Union, 1923-1943 (Box 10, Folder 107-109)
    - Buschke, Albrecht, et al., The Two-Move Chess Problem in the Soviet Union, 1923-1943 (Box 11, Folder 110-112)
    - Cahoon, Herbert, The Overbrook Press: Bibliography 1934-1959, 1958-1963 (Box 11, Folder 113-118)
    - Cahoon, Herbert, The Overbrook Press: Bibliography 1934-1959, 1958-1963 (Box 12, Folder 119-123)
    - California, State of California, Senate concurrent resolution no. 121: relative to congratulating and commending Lawrence Arnstein on a career of outstanding achievement in the field of public health: adopted in Senate May 15, 1957; adopted in Assembly June 4, 1957
    - Chiang Kai-Shek, Madame, Farewell Address, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Churchill, Winston S.
      - An Address Delivered in the House of Commons, November 30, 1950, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 125)
      - The Major Speeches by the Prime Minister of Great Britain, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Claudel, Paul, Paroles au Maechal: Poeme, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - Cleland, T. M. (Thomas Maitland)
      - "Progress" in the Graphic Arts: An Address Delivered at the Newberry Library in Chicago on November 5th, 1948, Before the Society of Typographic Arts, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 128)
      - "Progress" in the Graphic Arts [excerpt for A Keepsake for A.A. Knopf ], 1965 (Box 13, Folder 129)
      - 2 Letters in Praise of Progress in the Typographic and the Social Arts Addressed to Mr. Donald S. Klopfer, President, The American Institute of Graphic Arts, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Cohn, David L., America to England, by David L. Cohn; reprinted from The Atlantic Monthly August 1940 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Conant, James B., The Defense of Freedom, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Conklin, Grace Hazard, ["After Sunset"]: In Memory of Peggy Marshall, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - "Containment Plus": An Editorial from the Economist April 26, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Cook, Madge
      - Poems, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Thoughts in the Half Light, 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Council on Foreign Relations. Board of Directors, Edwin F. Gay 1867-1946: A Resolution (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Cousins, Norman, Amy Loveman, 1881-1955: A Eulogy, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Dedication of the Madeleine Borg Room, October 9, 1956: Women's Division of the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Dobbs, Gilbert, A Chess Silhouette: One Hundred Chess Problems; edited by Richard Cheney, Vincent Eaton, Otto Wurzburg [and] Alain White, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 140-141)
    - Dolbeare, Frederic R. and Gyula Dessewffy, Two Addresses Delivered at the Dedication of a New Transmitter of Radio Free Europe Beamed to Hungary, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 142)
    - Donors to the King George VI Memorial Fund, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - Douglas of Illinois, Editorial from The New York Times, October 20, 1966
    - Edman, Irwin, If Not, Not, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - Education for Responsibility: A Program of the Institute for Girls' and Women's Education To Be Held at New York University, Washington Square, New York City, October 20th and 21st, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 145)
    - Edwin Robert Anderson Seligman 1861-1939: Addresses Delivered at the Memorial Meeting Held on December the Thirteenth, 1941 in the Low Memorial Library at Columbia University, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 146)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D.
      - "Spirit of Geneva," excerpt from a speech delivered by President Eisenhower on August 24, 1955 at the annual convention of the American Bar Association, Independence Hall, Philadelphia
      - Tribute to Winston Spencer Churchill: Delivered Over the Facilities of the British Broadcasting Company at the Time of Sir Winston's Funeral, January 30, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 147)
    - Elizabeth II, A Message from Princess Elizabeth to British Children Abroad (issued as Christmas Greetings from Tula & Otto Jeidels ), 1944 (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - Emmet, Burton, Burton Emmett Collection: Notes for a Statement Regarding the Collection--In Case I Decide to Leave Such a Statement, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 149)
    - Emil Baerwald 1869-1948 (Box 14, Folder 150)
    - Etheridge, Mark F., "Of Whom Shall I Be Afraid?: A Commencement Address to Kentucky State College, June 2, 1953" (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, Soviet-American Relations: A Statement, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - France, Anatole, Affaire Crainquebille, illustrated by William Einstein, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 153)
      Includes a full set of original graphite drawings by Einstein for the book, and sets of lithographs made after the drawings.
    - Frank, Glenn, Problem of the Republican Program Committee: An Address at the First Meeting of the Republican Program Committee in Chicago, Feb. 28, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - Galantière, Lewis, America Today: A Freehand Sketch, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 155)
    - Galbraith, John Kenneth, How Keynes Came to America, circa 1965 (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - George Edgar Vincent: Addresses Delivered at the Memorial Services Held on May the Nineteenth, 1941, at the New York Academy of Medicine (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Gordan, Phyllis W. G., Fifteenth-Century Books in the Library of Howard Lehman Goodhart, 1952-1955 (Box 15, Folder 158-160)
    - Gordon-Taylor, Gordon, Sir., Citation Delivered by Sir Gordon Gordon-Taylor on the Occasion of the Award of the Honorary Fellowship in the Royal College of Surgeons of England to Richard Lewisohn, London, February 12, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Greenman, Frederick F., Wire-Tapping, Its Relation to Civil Liberties, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - Haight, Anne Lyon
      - Charles Dickens Tries to Remain Anonymous: Notes on the Loving Ballad of Lord Bateman, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 163)
      - Morals, Manners, Etiquette and the Three R's: From the Sixth to the Sixteenth Century, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 164)